Guide to the Harriet L. Clark Collection 1818-2001 MS010 MS010 MS010
Cornwall Historical Society
Harriet L. Clark Collection
1818-2001
, (Bulk [bulk start Year]-[bulk end Year])
Cornwall Historical Society
Clark, Harriet Lydia
MS010
3 linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection contains items relating to East Cornwall native Harriet Lydia Clark (1894-1997).
Provenance
This collection is made up of items that Clark both collected and wrote during her lifetime.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Harriet Lydia Clark (1894-1997) was descended from some of the earliest settlers in Cornwall, and maintained an interest in the history of both her family and community during her career as an educator and politician. She was born in East Cornwall to Andrew Miles Clark and Mary Brown Clark on November 11, 1894. After receiving degrees from both Boston University and Columbia University, Clark began a teaching career that took her to schools in locations such as East Cornwall, Warren, Goshen, and Danbury. Following her retirement from teaching, Clark was elected to the Connecticut House of Representatives in 1956, and represented Cornwall at the state assembly until 1965. Clark was a prolific genealogist and writer.
Sources:
Scope and Content Note
This collection is made up of six archival boxes. The first box contains bound items that belonged to the Clark family, and are organized in chronological order. The second box contains historic items relating to the Cornwall Clark family, as well as letters written by East Cornwall native Augustus White in 1852. White left East Cornwall to search for gold in California in 1852, and the letters he sent back to his family and friends in Connecticut detail his journey to the mining towns outside of San Francisco. The third box of this collection contains personal and memorial items of Harriet Clark, such as letters, and the fourth box contains publications that she wrote. The final two boxes contain scrapbooks compiled by Clark relating to her time as a state representative and her personal interest in the Foreign Mission School.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Bound Materials
Clark Family Materials
Harriet L. Clark Materials
Published Materials
Scrapbooks
[SH LCSH]; Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.)--Farming.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Pamphlets; Scrapbooks; Clark, Harriet Lydia; Clark, Harriet Lydia; Clark, Harriet Lydia; Obookiah, Henry, 1792-1818; Cornwall Historical Society
- Bound Materials
  - Account Books
    - M.S. Brown day book, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sheldon Clark grocery books, 1880-1888 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
    - A.M. Clark diary, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Andrew M. Clark accounts, 1895-1906 (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - Miscellaneous Bound Items
    - The Ladies Wreath and Parlor Annual, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Home Almanac, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gregory’s Annual Illustrated Retail Catalogue, 1884-1885 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Premium List: Connecticut State Agricultural Society, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cornwall Agricultural Society Treasurer’s Books, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - United Construction Co. day book, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Booklet from Litchfield Mutual Fire Insurance Company, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Clark Family Materials
  - Family Items
    - Pledge by neighbors of Jaleel Clark to help him after house fire, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Premiums awarded to Cornwall farmers at agricultural meeting in Litchfield, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - “Farmer’s Report", 1876 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Invitation sent to Mr. and Mrs. Andrew Clark for Fennell wedding reception, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dissertation, “Economic Development of Litchfield County,” by Loyal B. Clark, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Williams Clark Fertilizers booklet, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Clark Farm auction notice, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mohawk Farm property listing and aerial photograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Genealogies of Shepard-Tuttle-Barber families by Andrew Clark Pikosky, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - List of cow names on Clark family farm, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mohawk Farms butter packaging, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Augustus White Letters
    - Letter and obituary sent to H.L. Clark from Harriet E. Davis regarding Augustus White letters, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to his parents, Comfort and Maria, written from a ship sailing to California, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to his parents and friends, after landing in San Francisco, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to parents and friends about panning for gold, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Letter sent from Augusts White to his parents, about down time in California, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to his parents about struggles of mining gold, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to his sister about life in Cornwall, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Letter sent from Augustus White to his father, about work in California and the family farm, 1852 (Box 2)
- Harriet L Clark Materials
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Conn. Education Association, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letter from John Alsop, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letter from John Nicklas, director of Charlotte Hungerford Hospital, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Danbury State College, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letter from A. Searle Pinney, Conn. Republican Party Chairperson, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letter from Marion Treadwell, Danbury High School teacher, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letter from Conn. Education Association, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Ella T. Grasso, secretary of state, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letter from Mrs. William Goodman, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letter from R.E. Stumpe, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12-Nov)
    - Correspondence with Ann Hotchkiss, regarding Seelye family genealogy, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Letter from Rep. Nancy L. Johnson, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Letter to Michael Gannett from H.L. Clark, about Cornwall women voters, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence between Michael Gannett and H.L. Clark, regarding donation of Harriet L. Clark Collection, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Correspondence with Conn. Antique Machinery Association, about donated items, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Letter from Michael Gannett to David Clark, regarding donation made in memory of H.L. Clark, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Personal Papers
    - “A Brief History of the North Cornwall Grange No. 32,” by A.P. Brush, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
    - Premium lists for Cornwall Agricultural Society Fair and Field Day, 1913-1917 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Program for school closing exercises, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Blue ribbon from the Danbury Fair, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Employment papers from Mohawk State Park, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Image of Liberty Bell rug designed and hooked by H.L. Clark, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Graduation speech given at Cornwall Consolidated School, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Invitation to H.L. Clark’s 99th birthday, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - East Cornwall school documents, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Invitation to Conn. Education Association reception, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Personalized name cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Poem by cousin Jennie B. Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Christmas card, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Medical recipes, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Image of Liberty Bell souvenir owned by Mary Brown Clark, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - The Cornwall Star Vol I No. 2, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - The Litchfield Enquirer, 1882 (Box 3)
  - Memorial Items
    - Funeral program, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Invitation to July 4th celebration honoring H.L. Clark, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Political Items
    - List of Conn. Legislators, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Pocket manual, “Roll, Committees, and Rules of the General Assembly of Connecticut", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Laurel Club Bulletin No. 15, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Conn. United Republican Dinner Booklet, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Republican Convention Delegate ribbon, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Reception invitation to Republican Convention sent to women delegates, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Report of Interim Committee of Education, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - State representative card, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Education Bill No. 3232, introduced by Rep. Clark, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - The State Employee Vol. 19 No. 3, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Highway Association of Western Conn. letter to state legislature, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Testimonial Dinner to Honor Meade Alcorn and Republican Legislators program, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Fliers, “Vote Republican", 1962 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Invitation to Governor’s Prayer Breakfast, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - “House Journal” booklet, regarding US Supreme Court ruling, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Proclamation by Gov. John Dempsey, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Resolution of thanks to Rep. Clark from Conn. Education Committee, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Connecticut GOP Newsletter Vol. 1 No. 11, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Invitation to Connecticut Day at NY World’s Fair, as official guest of the governor, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Constitutional excerpt, Article III, Section I, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - State legislature campaign flier, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Cornwall ballots, undated (Box 3)
- Published Materials
  - Tracts by H.L. Clark
    - "When People Think of Spinsters", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - “Nina White and Mohawk Lookout", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - “The Romance of Mohawk Mountain", 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - “Little Old Stories of East Cornwall", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Article on butter-making, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - “Fire Watching From Mohawk Mountain", 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Poem, “I Clung Like A Miser", 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - “A Life in Cornwall", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - “1990 Christmas" (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - “Memories of Andrew Miles Clark", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - “Some Memories Of My Siblings", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - “A Winter of Lost Schooling Added Up to Pluses and Minuses", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "July 4th Celebrations", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - “Berrying", 1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - “A Raft of Troubles", undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - “Lydia Ann Clark Brown", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - “History of Fair in Cornwall", undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - “Cornwall Memories: The High Bridge", undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Image of hooks and eyes, with accompanying story, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - “Another Christmas Letter", undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - “Little Caroline", undated (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
    - Editorials, 1961-1965 (Box 4)
  - Articles Written by Others
    - Articles About H.L. Clark’s Political Career, 1957-1996; , undated (Box 4, Folder 52-61)
    - Articles about Clark family and Cornwall history, 1976-1986; , undated (Box 4, Folder 62-65)
    - Tributes and obituaries, 1979-1997 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Articles
    - Newspaper clipping on Campfire Girls, including H.L. Clark, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 67-68)
    - Articles on Clark and the Cornwall Covered Bridge renovation, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - “Cornwall” section of the Lakeville Journal, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - “Combined Report Traces Growth of Cornwall Historical Society", undated (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  - “A Collection of Interesting Things", 1936-1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General Assembly, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General Assembly, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Assembly, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cornwall Events, 1961-1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General Assembly, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Special Sessions, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Special Regular Session, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Cornwall People, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Opukahaia (Henry Obookiah), 1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)